Hello, today we are going to talk about something that a lot of people are very sensitive about.
你好，今天我們要談論一些很多人都很敏感的話題。
That is, how do you evolve from the sense of frustration that you have when communicating with an AI teacher
那就是，你如何從與 AI 老師溝通時的挫折感
to the sense that you can cooperate with it?
演變為你可以與它合作的感覺？
Are you ready to upgrade your AI skills together?
你準備好一起升級你的 AI 技能了嗎？
OK, let's get started!
好的，讓我們開始吧！
You must have had this experience, right?
你一定有過這種經驗，對吧？
That is, you think of a problem in your mind and send it out with full expectation.
那就是，你在腦海中想到一個問題，然後帶著滿懷期待發送出去。
As a result, you jump out of the screen with a completely straight face,
結果，螢幕上跳出來一個完全面無表情的，
or even a cold, unsatisfied request like this.
甚至冷冷的、令人不滿的回應就像這樣。
It's like you're talking to an AI, and then you hit a wall.
這就像你在和 AI 說話，然後你碰到了一堵牆。
It's really going to make people angry.
這真的會讓人生氣。
So, how do you break the wall of communication?
那麼，你如何打破溝通的隔閡呢？
What should you do to become a partner who can really guide the AI and think with it
你應該做什麼才能從只能給出簡單指令的使用者，
from a user who can only give simple instructions?
成為能真正引導 AI 並與它思考的合作夥伴？
Don't worry.
別擔心。
Today's content is going to give you a very clear and very structured roadmap.
今天的內容會給你一份非常清晰、結構很明確的路線圖。
We basically have three steps for today.
我們基本上今天有三個步驟。
First, plan your AI journey.
首先，規劃你的 AI 之旅。
Then, create your own reminder toolbox.
然後，創建你自己的提示詞工具箱。
Finally, the most fun step is to practice through games.
最後，最有趣的一步是通過遊戲進行練習。
Follow these three steps, and you can step by step become an AI partner.
按照這三個步驟，你可以一步步成為 AI 合作夥伴。
Okay, let's start from the first step.
好的，讓我們從第一步開始。
Plan your AI journey.
規劃你的 AI 之旅。
The key to this step is to help yourself build a system-based growth plan.
這一步的關鍵是幫助自己建立一個系統化的成長計劃。
This is not to blindly practice, but to strategically improve yourself,
這不是盲目練習，而是戰略性地提升自己，
so that you can build a stable foundation for later progress.
這樣你就能為之後的進步奠定穩固的基礎。
Now, let's take a look at this super useful self-evaluation tool.
現在，讓我們來看看這個超實用的自我評估工具。
It covers the core capabilities of four cooperation with AI,
它涵蓋了與 AI 合作的四個核心能力，
which is to make the goal clear.
也就是讓目標更清晰。
Develop is to make your ideas better step by step.
Develop 是讓你的想法一步步變得更好。
Direct is to give accurate instructions.
Direct 是給出準確的指令。
And discern is to evaluate whether the AI is doing well.
而 Discern 是評估 AI 做得是否好。
You can use this table to honestly evaluate yourself on these four projects.
你可以用這個表格老實地評估自己在這四個項目上的水平。
Are you a beginner? Are you still improving? Are you already very confident?
你是初學者嗎？你還在進步中嗎？你已經很有把握了嗎？
Then, write down your strengths and where you need to strengthen.
然後，寫下你的優勢和你需要加強的地方。
Do you know where you are now? Is it the first step of the planning route?
你知道你現在在哪裡嗎？這是規劃路線的第一步。
Okay, after the evaluation, we come to the specific action plan.
好的，評估之後，我們來到具體的行動計劃。
It's very simple, four steps.
非常簡單，四個步驟。
First, evaluate your current capabilities.
首先，評估你目前的能力。
Second, from those four capabilities, choose one or two goals that you think you need to strengthen the most.
其次，從那四個能力中，選擇一到兩個你認為最需要加強的目標。
Then, plan specific practice activities and time tables.
然後，計劃具體的練習活動和時間表。
The most important step is coming.
最重要的一步即將到來。
You need to have a very clear definition of how much progress and success you have made.
你需要非常清楚地定義你取得了多少進展和成功。
In this way, your goal is no longer vague, I want to become strong,
這樣，你的目標就不再是模糊的「我想變強」，
but a plan that can be carried out step by step.
而是一個可以逐步執行的計劃。
Okay, when you have drawn your own learning route,
好的，當你繪製了自己的學習路線，
the next step is of course to prepare the equipment.
下一步當然是準備設備。
So we come to the second stage,
所以我們進入第二階段，
build your exclusive reminder toolbox.
建立你專屬的提示詞工具箱。
It's a little bit like preparing the most common things you usually do with the most effective tools.
有點像用最有效的工具來準備你平常最常做的事情。
Let your efficiency fly straight.
讓你的效率直線上升。
So, what is the reminder toolbox?
那麼，什麼是提示詞工具箱？
It's a secret weapon toolbox that belongs to you.
這是一個屬於你的祕密武器工具箱。
It contains the most effective reminder words that you can use directly,
它包含你可以直接使用的最有效的提示詞，
various good strategies,
各種好的策略，
and those that you think AI has done very well.
以及那些你認為 AI 做得很好的東西。
This is not just a copy and paste,
這不僅僅是複製貼上，
this is the experience of working with AI.
這是與 AI 合作的經驗。
What should be in a good reminder toolbox?
一個好的提示詞工具箱應該包含什麼？
Well, you can start with these aspects.
嗯，你可以從這些方面開始。
First, help you build some templates for the five to ten tasks you do most often.
首先，幫助你為你最常做的五到十項任務建立一些模板。
Write down what you think are the most useful description strategies.
寫下你認為最有用的描述策略。
Also, how do you judge whether AI has done well?
同時，你如何判斷 AI 做得是否良好？
Record these identification models.
記錄這些識別模式。
Finally, collect some successful examples that you can refer to in the future.
最後，收集一些你將來可以參考的成功案例。
When you start building this toolbox,
當你開始建立這個工具箱時，
you will find that the quality of your communication with AI will really improve steadily.
你會發現你與 AI 的溝通品質會真正穩步提高。
Well, the last stop of the journey is also the most interesting stop I think.
嗯，旅程的最後一站也是我認為最有趣的一站。
Practice through games.
通過遊戲進行練習。
Hey, don't underestimate this thing.
嘿，不要小看這個東西。
It's not just fun.
這不僅僅是有趣。
It's a great training ground.
它是一個很好的訓練場。
Let's take a look at an example.
讓我們看一個例子。
This is a game called exchange guessing games.
這是一個叫做交換猜謎遊戲的遊戲。
On the left is a puzzle.
左邊是一個謎題。
I hit more than a hundred drums to draw out the sound of light.
我敲打超過一百個鼓來發出光的聲音。
What am I doing?
我在做什麼？
The answer is actually typing on a computer keyboard.
答案其實是在電腦鍵盤上打字。
But here's the point.
但重點是這個。
Look at what's written on the right.
看看右邊寫的是什麼。
The real goal is not to guess the correct answer by AI,
真正的目標不是讓 AI 猜對答案，
but to analyze its reasoning process.
而是分析它的推理過程。
When it guesses wrong,
當它猜錯時，
you don't just tell it the answer.
你不只是告訴它答案。
Instead, you guide it to think.
相反，你引導它去思考。
See if you can help it get back on the right track.
看看你能否幫助它重新走上正軌。
Before we continue to play,
在我們繼續遊戲之前，
let's pause and talk about a core skill that we are practicing.
讓我們暫停一下，談談我們正在練習的一項核心技能。
This word is very important.
這個詞非常重要。
It's called identification.
它叫做辨識。
It's a very critical ability.
這是一項非常關鍵的能力。
It means that you have to be able to assess the production and thinking process of AI,
這意味著你必須能夠評估 AI 的產出和思考過程，
and then guide the model to get a better result.
然後引導模型獲得更好的結果。
To be honest,
說實話，
this is the biggest difference between professionals and ordinary users.
這是專業人士和普通用戶之間最大的區別。
This identification can be divided into three types.
這個辨識可以分為三種類型。
The first is result identification,
第一種是結果辨識，
which is to see if the answer given by AI is logical.
就是看 AI 給出的答案是否合乎邏輯。
The second is process identification,
第二種是過程辨識，
which is to see how AI came up with the answer,
就是看 AI 是如何想出答案的，
and what its thinking process is.
以及它的思考過程是什麼。
The third is performance identification,
第三種是表達辨識，
which is to see if AI has made it clear.
就是看 AI 是否表達清楚。
When you are playing a game or thinking,
當你玩遊戲或思考時，
you can practice these three types of identification.
你可以練習這三種辨識。
Besides guessing,
除了猜測之外，
there are many other fun ways to practice.
還有許多其他有趣的方式來練習。
For example, 20 questions,
例如，20 問遊戲，
how to tell a story,
如何講故事，
how to play a role,
如何扮演角色，
you can even give AI a very complex concept,
你甚至可以給 AI 一個非常複雜的概念，
but ask it to use super strict restrictions to explain.
但要求它用非常嚴格的限制來解釋。
For example,
例如，
you can only use main dishes to compare.
你只能用主菜來比較。
These ways of playing to improve your communication skills are super helpful.
這些通過玩遊戲來改進溝通技能的方式非常有幫助。
I think this sentence is a great summary.
我認為這句話是一個很好的總結。
The guidance skills learned in the game
在遊戲中學到的引導技能
will be amazingly practical in real projects.
在實際專案中將發揮驚人的實用性。
This is the key.
這是關鍵所在。
The skills you learn in the process of playing
你在玩遊戲過程中學到的技能
can be directly applied to your profession,
可以直接應用到你的職業上，
or even on a very high-risk job.
甚至應用在風險很高的工作上。
So, this is not a waste of time.
所以，這不是浪費時間。
You are making the most effective investment.
你在做最有效的投資。
So, AI is your new partner in thinking.
所以，AI 是你思考的新夥伴。
After this journey from planning,
經過這段從規劃開始的旅程，
to making tools, to real-life eye-catching,
到製作工具，到真實生活中引人注目的應用，
are you ready to lead this conversation?
你準備好引領這場對話了嗎？